Hey English learners, welcome to this A2
English listening practice video. Today
I'm gonna talk about relearning a
language. So I am currently relearning
Greek right now. It's not the first time
that I've learned it. Uh, I studied
Greek many years ago and I stopped about
four and a half years ago or maybe a
little bit more than that. Uh, but now
I'm relearning Greek. And I'd like to
talk about that today. Uh, because it's
a pretty interesting process to relearn
a language. It's not the same thing as
learning a language for the first time.
So, I'll talk about some of those
differences today and some of the things
I've been experiencing
uh while relearning Greek. And uh I hope
that you enjoy this video. And of
course, it's good practice for your
listening. If you feel like you need to
uh advance more and you want to get
better at understanding fast English,
then make sure to check out my advanced
podcast episodes. If you want those, the
link is down below. In those episodes, I
speak at normal speed, not slowly like
in these videos. By the way, people
sometimes ask me if uh they uh speed up
these YouTube videos like make it faster
if that's the same thing as using my
advanced episodes. It's not. You can do
that with these YouTube videos. But when
I slow down my speech, like in these
videos, I change the way that I stress
and reduce words. It's not the same as
when I speak normally. Uh, and so if you
make these videos faster, it's not the
same thing as the way I say words and
phrases when I speak in my advanced
episodes, by the way, because yes,
you're making this video faster, so
that's good. But it's not going to sound
natural uh with the same type of stress
and reduced speech and uh rhythm as a
normal
video or uh podcast episode uh where I'm
speaking at normal speed. So I just
wanted to mention that because people
always ask about that. Okay, let's talk
about relearning a language. I started
relearning Greek maybe four weeks ago,
something like that. Uh, so it's pretty
recent, but I've already learned a lot
and I've learned some lessons from these
weeks of relearning Greek. So when you
learn a language for the first time,
it's the first time you've seen it.
You're creating new connections in your
brain. Okay? Uh this is uh a different
process from when you're relearning a
language. Uh when you're learning a
language for the first time, it's really
easy to forget things. It's very easy to
see a word, even a simple word like
great or something, and you see it, you
note it down, and you forget it
afterwards. That's really common when
you're learning a language for the first
time. This is because you have no
foundation, you have no base. So, you're
just seeing new things that have no
significance to you and you've never
seen anything like that before and
things just don't make sense to you yet.
And a big thing is that things don't
sound right or wrong to you yet. Uh, now
you're learning English. You're not a
native speaker, but I'm sure if you hear
another English learner say something
uh that's really incorrect, you can
probably feel that it's wrong. You
probably feel that it's incorrect even
though you're not a native speaker. And
when you're learning a language for the
first time, you're just starting out,
you have no foundation, you don't have
this feeling of right and wrong. Um, you
don't know what sounds right. You don't
know what sounds wrong. Everything is
just completely new and arbitrary,
meaning uh it's kind of random. you
don't have any connection with these
sounds or words uh or grammar. It's all
new for you. On the other hand, when you
relearn a language, you're not starting
from scratch. Even if you think you've
forgotten everything, you haven't. It's
not completely gone. Maybe you can't
think of that thing in that moment. Uh
but that information might still be deep
down in your brain. This is something
I've noticed. Uh before this past month,
I felt like I just did not have any
Greek in my brain. like I forgot almost
everything except for some basic things.
Uh but even though it feels like this,
even though it feels like the
information you've learned is completely
gone, it's not. So, uh in the past
month, I've been relearning Greek. And
like I said before this, I couldn't say
anything. I didn't remember how to say
things or uh I couldn't understand
things. It seemed like the words were
gone. But when I started relearning
Greek, I realized, oh, I recognize that
word. Oh, yeah. I know that word. Oh, of
course I know that word. that's been
happening over and over again throughout
this past month. And so I realize that
this information has not completely
disappeared.
I just have to revive it, bring it back
to life. Okay. So let me talk about some
things that I've been noticing. Like as
soon as I see or hear a word that I used
to know, I have this click. I recognize
it immediately. Oh yeah, I remember that
word that keeps happening over and over
again. And it's like uh we say this in
English like a light bulb moment where
the light bulb goes off like oh yeah wow
that's right I've been having this again
and again uh suddenly this word comes
back to me like oh yeah I know that word
and then suddenly it's obvious like oh
Of course, I know how to say that. Uh,
and that's strange because right before
that, it's like I had no idea how to say
that word. I had no idea what that word
was in Greek, but then suddenly I see it
and then it's super obvious. It's not
like when you're learning a language for
the first time and you see a new word
and it's like, "Okay, another new word
to learn." Uh, and it has no meaning for
you yet. When I relearn these Greek
words, I see it and immediately it has
meaning. Immediately I remember that
word. Immediately
I it re-establishes that connection in
my brain. It's really cool. I've even
started remembering
other words, other random words without
even seeing them or hearing them again.
So one thing is when I relearn the word,
I see it or I hear it and I say, "Oh
yeah, I remember that word." But I'm
also experiencing this where I don't
even see the word or hear the word and I
just remember suddenly how to say drive
or some random verb like I'm just
practicing and suddenly I go, "Oh, I
remember that drive is this word." Even
though no one said it, I didn't see it
anywhere. I just randomly remember how
to say that word. That's happened a
number of times already. So, uh, as I'm
relearning Greek,
information is surfacing as we say,
meaning it's coming and, uh, becoming
visible and uh, suddenly I know it
again. even uh in some cases when I
don't even see the word, I just randomly
remember how to say certain things or
maybe I'm going to uh look something up
and before I even see the result, I kind
of remember like, oh, I think it starts
with this letter. And then I look up the
word and I realize that yes, it starts
with that letter. So all of this is uh
reviving. It's coming back to me. It's
coming back to life. And I feel that
relearning all of this information,
relearning words and phrases and all of
that, uh, it's making these connections
stronger in my brain. When I first
learned these words and these phrases,
the connection was not that strong. And
so I had to um strengthen this
connection over time by seeing the word
or hearing the word again and again. But
now when I relearn a word, I have that
connection more quickly. I don't need to
see it as many times again to really
establish it in my brain. I remember it
better. It has more meaning for me uh
quicker, more quickly. So, uh I think
that forgetting something and then
relearning it is a very powerful thing.
Uh I know there's research about this.
I'm not really familiar with all of the
studies and the results, but I'm pretty
sure that there is uh established
science about this about forgetting
things and then relearning them and how
uh that's a really powerful thing. So,
um, the fact that I've forgotten all of
these words and phrases in Greek and now
I'm relearning them, that's a powerful
way to establish strong connections in
my brain. So, I guess a lesson that you
can take from that is that you shouldn't
be afraid to forget things. Sometimes we
have this fear of forgetting
information, forgetting words that we
learn. Don't worry about this. You'll
relearn them when it's necessary, when
you need to, and then you'll probably
remember these words even better, once
you relearn them. That's what's
happening to me right now in Greek. I
think that I'm going to remember my
vocabulary now better than before. And I
think the process of reaching the level
that I was at when I stopped is going to
be a lot faster uh than the process of
reaching that level for the first time.
So uh if it took me a year to reach a
certain level before, maybe it will only
take me eight months now or something.
Uh, I'm just randomly saying numbers
here. I don't know. But I feel like the
process is going to be faster now that
I'm relearning Greek uh and not learning
it uh from scratch for the first time.
So, uh, remember that I haven't learned
Greek in a long time, like over four and
a half years. It's been quite a while
since I've learned Greek, and that's a
long time, but the knowledge that I have
of Greek is still there in my brain. So,
that's really cool because sometimes we
can think that when we stop learning a
language and we take a long break that
we've wasted our time. Ah, I wasted a
year and a half learning English years
ago and now uh I have to start again.
Why did I stop? I wasted that time. And
of course, it's better not to stop
learning the language. But what's cool
is that you didn't waste your time. I
didn't waste my time learning Greek in
the past. I felt like that maybe last
year when I didn't know any Greek and I
couldn't remember anything and I thought
h ah why did I spend all that time and
then stop but now I realize that that
time that effort that energy that I
spent many years ago was not in vain
meaning it was not useless it actually
had results and now I'm benefiting from
that. I'm relearning Greek and the
process is going faster than when I
first learned it and I'm remembering
these words that I learned. I'm reviving
them. That knowledge is still deep in my
brain. So, I'm very happy about that. I
hope that if you've had this experience
of learning a language and stopping, I
hope now that you realize that you can
revive a lot of that information and
establish stronger connections now. So,
uh don't be too discouraged if that has
happened to you. Remember that you can
check out my advanced podcast episodes
in which I speak fast by clicking on the
link down below and signing up for
those. So, make sure to challenge
yourself and use that advanced content
so you can reach the next level in your
English listening. Okay, thank you all
for watching this A2 English listening
practice video and I'll talk to you in
the next